All right, thank you very much Salim for
joining. Let me start asking straight,
right? So, you have said somewhere that
we are living through the most important
decade of the human history. So, can you
please explain why?
>> So, there there are two things happening
in technology that we have never seen
before and I think it's worth
just touching on those two things
because it forms the foundation of
what's happening at a broader scale,
right? So, the first thing is that we
have we've seen Moore's law for 60
years, right? Double every 18 months.
Well, we now have a dozen technologies
that are operating on a doubling pattern
and we've just never seen this in human
history. Throughout history, maybe one
technology is accelerating or another.
We've never seen this many all move at
the same time. For example, drones are
doubling every 9 months in their price
performance. Solar energy every 22
months and has been doing that for 40
years. In neuroscience, the resolution
at which we can image the brain is
doubling every year. So, so fact one is
we have all of these technologies on an
accelerated path. So, that's the first
thing. But, the second thing is actually
more the most interesting thing, which
is the cost. So, throughout human
history, it turns out advanced
technologies cost a lot, right? And only
a government or a big corporate lab
could do R&D, launch new products and
services. Today, for the first time in
human history, advanced technologies are
very cheap. So, you can spend $20 a
month or a million dollars a month on
AI, you're getting basically the same
outcome. Blockchains are open source and
free. This has never been possible
before to do very disruptive innovation
at near zero cost. So, this kind of
completely opens up the playing field to
disruptive innovation exploding out of
every corner of the world.
>> Okay. All right. So, you and Peter came
up with the concept long back about six
Ds, right? Can you if you don't mind,
can you quickly explain? I know most of
people know what is six Ds means, but
just to simplify the things if you can
explain what is six Ds.
>> So, so six Ds was coined by Peter
Diamandis and Steven Kotler in their
book Abundance.
And we've been using that structure ever
since. It basically means when you
digitize there's several forces have
happened with a technology today, which
is first is we're digitizing the world,
right? That's pretty obvious. Our brain
Our memories aren't in our heads,
they're in our smartphones. All we have
wearables that are digitizing health
information, etc. The second is when you
digitize things become very, very
disruptive and they enter an exponential
growth path. Okay? And so, as you turn
something to an information-based
paradigm, it goes to exponential growth.
Okay? The third thing is very, very
disruptive. Sorry, deceptive. It doesn't
look like anything's happening. So,
people just kind of ignore it. And
there's a really big challenge that
people don't understand exponential
growth. Human beings don't understand
exponential. Our brains simply don't see
it. They're not We're not able to
calculate at that level. Okay? The
simple example I give is if you take a
piece of 8 1/2 by 11 or A4 paper, which
is 0.1 mm thick, and you fold it, it
becomes 0.2 mm, right? Fold it again, it
becomes 0.4. Here's a question you can
all ask yourselves. How thick is it if
you fold it 50 times? Okay? And nobody
will get that answer. Okay? Some people
go, maybe it's this thick. Some people
go, maybe it's the thickness of the
room. No, it turns out at 38 folds
you've gone around the sun. And at the
50th fold you've gone to Sorry, at the
38th fold you've gone around the Earth.
At the 50th fold you've gone to the sun.
Okay? Now, granted that folding the last
few ones is not trivial. But that's
ridiculous. And nobody will calculate
that, right? No human being has an
innate ability calculate exponential.
So, we just don't see it. So, that's the
deceptive part. The third thing is when
you end up in this model, you then end
up demonetizing
things very radically because the cost
drops. As I said, the I digital domain
is much more cheaper. It democratizes,
which is the effect of demonetization.
And it democratizes, meaning it spreads
everywhere. And because the cost has
gone, it propagates powerfully. Look at
the speed of acceleration of Open AI and
AI adoption around the world. I'm going
to So, those six things are happening
now in more and more domains and this is
why we have so much disruption
occurring. We've just never seen
anything like this before. I'll give you
two quick examples. If Vitalik Buterin,
18-year-old kid out of Toronto, gets
together with a few friends, they ignore
their professors and boom, you have
Ethereum, ready $400 billion ecosystem
that I joke that nobody understands,
right?
I My other favorite example is there's a
car called the Vega. Okay?
>> Okay.
>> It's eight 900 horsepower. It's the
third fastest car ever built, okay?
And this was designed and engineered and
built in Sri Lanka,
>> Okay.
>> that that hotbed of automotive
innovation, right? Now, now, tell me how
an island of essentially fishermen and
farmers where they have no ecosystem,
investors, education, uh experience is
able to build the third fastest car ever
built, right? That's what's possible
today.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, that means that we're going to
see the most unbelievable explosion of
innovation from every corner of the
world.
>> Okay. All right. So, last week or I
think uh week before last week, right?
China's Moonshot AI
released Kimi K3, right? With uh I think
2.8 trillion parameters. Do you think
that is I mean, how do you see with the
6D lens?
>> So, we think this is one of the biggest
inflection points in human technology.
>> All right.
>> Right? Well, why? Because now that you
have a very robust open-source model and
they released the weights, anybody can
grab that model
>> Correct.
>> and go use it for any particular purpose
they want, right? Now, the cyber folks
freak out, oh my god, people are going
to do bad things with it. Yes. What
we've seen with technology throughout
history is you have bad use cases, you
have good use cases, right? I I use fire
to heat my house and I can use it to
burn down your house. Over the
centuries, we've done a pretty good job
of extracting the promise of technology
without the peril. Okay?
The amplitude of the negative is
increasing radically. So, that's of
concern today. How do you navigate? You
could use ChemK3 to engineer a virus
that hopped across people and took out
middle-aged bald Indian people, which I
would not be very happy about, right?
And how do you How do you navigate and
protect against that? But, the upside is
kind of very profound. And I think we
tend to focus on that on Moonshots just
because of that. So, we think it's one
of the biggest inflection points ever
because now you can use that model to
train smaller models, more specialized
models. So, it this basically opens up
the playing field. Again, cost zero. You
just need compute now.
>> Got it.
>> And that's that's dropping at like a
stone. The cost of tokens, I think,
dropped 280 times last year.
>> Right.
>> And it's on track to do something
similar this year.
>> Okay.
So, so I mean, from the cybersecurity
point of view, right? Because our
audience is very eager to know the
impact on the cybersecurity on that,
right? So, their their worry is like
ChemK3, anyone can use it virtually, and
then we have these quantum chips
probably up by 2029, and then these kind
of models along with the quantum, how do
you see the cybersecurity as a threat?
>> So, cyber and security in general is an
arms race, right? The bad guys do
something negative, and we figure it
out. Okay? If you go back through
history, we thought, "My god, email is
going to crash because of all the spam."
Then we thought, "Oh my god, there'll be
fishing attacks, and we'll totally crash
collapse that." And we What would we We
used AI to solve email spam, right? And
we have pretty robust email spam filters
now that do a really good job of that. I
think it's the same challenge and the
same outcome where you'll have a quantum
breakthrough, and people start doing
negative things with it, and then we'll
figure out other ways of doing it. The
problem is you want to keep that gap as
narrow as possible, right? And and I was
talking to Jay Chaudhry, CEO of Zscaler,
right? And also I've interacted with the
CEO of Palo Alto Networks over the
years. And something they said to me
really struck me, which is the way we do
cyber has not changed in 20 years. And
that is very, very alarming because you
can't use the same organizational design
process frameworks to do something 20
years ago that you're doing today. It
that is absolutely not going to scale.
And the technology is workable. The
problem is the adoption speed of the
defensive co-scaling of the technology
is the biggest and most dangerous and
most vulnerable weak point is our
ability to figure out defensive
co-scaling of these AI systems to keep
pace with that.
>> Yeah, okay. Now, in terms of AGI, right?
And I've been listening to your podcast.
So, what do you what is your thought on
AGI, right? Now, just to simplify.
>> Alex is very clear we achieved AGI like
5, 6 years ago, right? And all we're
doing is is scaling it.
I was talking to the chief security
officer at of Anthropic over the last
couple of days, and he thinks we hit AGI
in 2 to 3 years. He does not think it's
here yet. So, there's a very wide
variety of
experts. I you you've heard my beef. We
have I don't think we know what
intelligence is. So, you know, AGI it's
not really artificial, it's not really
general, it's not really intelligent.
Other than that, it's it's fine. You
know, so so how do you we have a huge
definition problem, right? We have a
definition problem, and we have a a
benchmarks problem. You know, I I think
we keep moving the posts on AGI like we
did Turing the Turing test. At some
point we'll achieve it and blow past it,
and nobody will basically notice is my
is my thing. The best for if you ask me,
what is my definition of AGI, I will go
with Reid Hoffman's definition, which is
he said, "Look, you could spend a
lifetime becoming the world's best
marine biologist, right? You could spend
a lifetime becoming the world's best
accountant. You could spend a lifetime
becoming the world's best theoretical
mathematician, okay? And in normal
environments, that those domains never
cross, ever, right? Now, but AI can
actually merge those two and intersect
those two. And what would happen if you
took the expertise of accounting and
match merged it with marine biology?
Something really interesting may happen
at those intersections, and we can now
explore those in a way that human beings
could not explore those, right? I think
that's a hint. And I I look at also, if
you take PageRank, Google's AI that's
scanning trillions of web pages, it's
developing a completely orthogonal form
of intelligence that is complementary to
human intelligence, not replicative,
right? When you say AGI, people always
jump straight to, "Oh my god, human
beings will be replaced," etc., etc. And
I just don't buy that. I think we'll
create complementary forms of
intelligence that will be additive to
what we're able to do, okay? My memory
is not not in my head anymore, it's in
my smartphone. Nobody wants a memory in
their heads anymore. It's flawed, right?
Now, I've got a whole bunch of neurons
that are freed up that could do much
more interesting work. And so, I think
we'll create forms of what I would call
AGI is complementary forms of
intelligence, cognitive processing, uh
analytic abilities, etc., that will
enhance my capabilities, right? Now, my
capabilities then become my pure
creativity, how resilient how to do I
want to be, what what thought processes
do I want to have in my head, what how
do I train my neural network to be the
most optimal. And from an And you know,
I'll just use an Indian perspective, as
AI and robots take on more and more
doing, right? It gives us humans the
opportunity to do more and more being.
And the best being technology in the
world is in India.
>> Yeah.
>> Cuz we're really good at being a
meditation, presencing, etc. Just take
the concept of presence. Where is that
in any equation around AI? And yet, it's
a fundamentally important phenomena
around the subjective experience of
being alive, right? And so, I I I think
the argument around AGI is a flawed
argument trying to map it onto human
intelligence, and I don't think it maps.
>> Okay. All right. Perfect. No, makes
sense. Quickly
changing tangent a little bit, right?
So, we have been dealing with many of
the enterprises. What we have seen is
the AI agents
or agentic applications are working
great in the proof of concept, but the
moment it hits the production load, we
are seeing a lot of restraint in terms
of how we are using the data, and then
the agents basically performs perfectly
fine. It's supposed to be, right? So,
there are there are some sort of
restraint. Again, it depends upon orgs
to orgs, as you know, but it it There is
some kind of restraint among the
enterprises
that
agents are not performing well. So, what
is your What is your opinion? Why Why
that is happening?
>> So, I've been studying organizational
design for almost 20 years now, right?
The first book I wrote, Exponential
Organizations. Can I give you a little
bit of theory here?
>> Absolutely. That was my next question,
but you we can go ahead with this
exponential organization.
>> it's important to understand the theory
of how we have designed organizations up
to now and what's breaking, right? So,
back in 1937, an economist at the
University of Chicago called Ronald
Coase, c o a s e,
asked the question. And the question he
asked was, "Why do companies exist? If I
can contract for goods and services in
the marketplace, why do I need a firm?"
Right? I need distant research. And he
wrote a paper called The Nature of the
Firm and published it saying that the
reason you have companies is
coordination and execution costs are
cheaper inside a company than outside.
The poster child is the Ford Model T
assembly line is able to assemble cars
that are much lower cost, sell those
cars on the outside and make that
margin, right? He won the Nobel Prize
for this paper, by the way.
Since then, all organizational design
has followed from that fundamental
thesis, like all, okay? Human hierarchy
gives us coordination and execution
costs cheaper than the outside world,
okay? In 2014, we noticed something that
we were starting to reach outside the
organization to get things done. Take
the mission-critical of Uber, which is
to match driver and passenger, doesn't
happen inside the Uber organizational
boundary, happens out in the wild, and
by enabling that with technology, they
can scale, right? Because now you're not
limited by the organizational boundaries
to scale your organization, which is
kind of interesting. We didn't quite
cotton on to how big a deal that was at
the time. We just kind of observed, hey,
people are Ted is using its community to
scale, right? X Prize uses crowd
competitions to scale, etc.
In the second edition of the book, which
came out in 2023, we declared Coase's
Law dead, but didn't give it any kind of
solid form, but now we declare it
completely dead, or not dead, but
obsolete. The conditions have changed
because execution costs inside a company
are now more expensive than outside a
company, okay? Try and get a web page
built inside your company, the IT folks
don't have time, go file a ticket, the
branding people don't want you to be
doing that, the CIO is not happy, and
and you can spend weeks and weeks,
committees, approval levels, trying to
get a web page up. Meanwhile, you can go
home and Vercel and build it in 5
minutes for free with AI,
>> Absolutely.
>> okay? That is a massive impedance
mismatch, okay? There was a fellow that
tweeted, I think his name is Todd
Saunders, he tweeted a comment which I
think nails it. He said, today it's
cheaper to build a product feature than
to have the meeting about building the
product feature.
>> Absolutely.
>> Now, that
>> [laughter]
>> that should just blow everybody's mind,
right? So, this means something
fundamental has changed, and we call
that the organizational singularity,
meaning we have to redesign our
organization. Reason you're seeing all
these AI efforts fail is we're trying to
cram AI into legacy human higher centric
hierarchical structures and all you're
doing is accelerating the human
bottleneck, okay? The best visual I will
tell give you is when we first invented
television,
right? We took radio announcers reading
radio scripts in front of a camera,
okay?
>> Okay.
>> And you're not leveraging the medium at
all and frankly most radio announcers
are not good looking enough to be on
television, right? So you've got the
wrong you're doing the wrong thing in
the wrong way. So that's what we're
doing today with AI. We have to redesign
the organization fundamentally go
rethink
the basis of human interaction and
that's what we've done. We've released a
book over the last couple of months
called the organizational singularity.
>> Okay.
>> basic thesis it's it's at openexo.com
it's free to use. We've actually
released a cloud skill for the book that
helps you just leverage the book because
I'm updating it on a weekly basis.
>> Okay.
>> it's because the minute I hit print it's
out of date, right? This is which is an
indication of that volatility we're
talking about. So the question becomes
what does it should it look like? And
we've spent some time theorizing what
does the organizational structure of the
future look like and what we've come up
with is at the core of the organization
you need an
set of AI agent layers a bit like an
OODA loop.
>> Okay.
>> Boyd in the 70s coined this phrase came
up with this phrase is used in the
military a lot which is observe, orient,
decide, act. Okay? Simple feedback loop
except the basis of that becomes your
heart of your organization and then you
layer workflows and data on top of that
engine, okay? So I'll give you an
example. If you take invoice processing
in a company, okay? Invoice comes in
first thing it does it runs to
accounting,
right? The accounting department goes
and looks at it and says is there
actually a customer a vendor, for this
invoice, right? Then it goes to
operations did the uh work get done.
Then it goes to legal, what are the
payment terms and where does that go?
Then it goes back to accounting, when do
we schedule the payment, has it been
approved? Every single spot is a human
bottleneck in that loop.
>> Right.
>> You may automate a little bit with the
ERP systems, but you still have human
approval at all those spots in various
ways. The same goes for delivery
receipts, the same goes for content
management. It's all human-centric
approval loops. When you put AI into
that, you're accelerating the
human-to-human bottleneck. That's the
radio over TV analogy, right? What you
have to do is redesign that entire
workflow to be AI-centric. And then what
happens is every single time you run the
loop, you have the learning level where
the AI is asking, how can I improve that
loop?
>> Okay.
>> Now, what how what do you achieve by
that? It's very important. In the AI
model world, there's been a term that's
being thrown around called recursive
self-improvement,
>> Right.
>> right? If you went back 18 months ago,
about 10% of one version of Claude was
used to write the next version of
Claude.
>> Okay.
>> By the end of last year, it was about
50%.
>> Okay.
>> Uh we're up to 88% now for the big
models and 100% for the small models.
So, in fact, OpenAI just announced this,
where they said they're using the big
model to do the building of the smaller
models, okay?
>> Mhm.
>> So, we've hit recursive
self-improvement. That's a crazy bar,
because once you hit that, we hit the
singularity where we don't know how fast
this is going to go. Now, the the bar
for getting recursive self-improvement
at a workflow level is much, much lower,
right? Cuz all I have to do is figure
out, how do I improve this process, make
it faster, cheaper, better, smaller.
When you look at AI-native firms that
are operating in a truly AI-native way,
we're seeing about a 100x performance
compared to the legacy. So, if your
invoice processing system was doing a
thousand invoices a month, an AI-native
system is doing about a hundred thousand
invoices a a month.
Okay? Now, so if you can build your firm
in an AI native way, you're going to
strip away any ability to compete,
right? And so, we think every And And
this is not every company. This is every
nonprofit. This is every government
department. Anywhere where we have human
organization, we will move it to this
new model because it's just better and
better by like a hundred times. So, I
think that's the future. How we get
there is the enormous structural
challenge. And this is where we're doing
a lot of work on the methodologies
around that. And I can cover some of
that if that's interesting
>> Yeah, I know. Absolutely. That is I
think that is part of Open EXO, right?
If I'm not wrong, is Salim?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah, so can you be because I have a
simple question, right? So, let's say a
mid-market company who is actually in
some sort of retailing business, and
they want to have AI. And they want to
like AI first org, right? So, how this
Open EXO framework helps that? If you
can just summarize what is Open EXO, and
then yeah.
>> Yeah, so Open EXO is a community of
advi- We have advisors. We have 50,000
people around the world in 150
countries. And it's a global community
of people that are fascinated and
interested in the model that I've We've
created. We use the community to help
build the model. So, it's a collective
approach. And then we've solved a couple
of problems, okay? One of the big
problems we've solved is If you have a
big company and you try anything
disruptive, the immune system attacks
you, okay? Because all organizations are
built to resist change and withstand
risk. Default answer in a big company if
you try anything disruptive is no,
right? Or in France, they go "Pas
possible." In Germany, they go "Nein."
And in India, you just get a head shake
saying "No buddy. Not possible." Okay.
So, so that's the default answer. We've
learned how to turn that default answer
from a no to a yes, okay? So, we piloted
a 10-week engagement in 2015 with
Procter & Gamble. Uh cuz the
CIO called me and said, "We want to work
with you. Your book is required
reading." And we crafted a 10-week
engagement cuz I said, "I want to solve
that immune system problem." Before
Procter & Gamble, I was the global head
of I was the head of innovation at
Yahoo.
>> Yeah.
>> Running their incubator. And we came
across this problem. The more disruptive
an idea we came up with in the
incubator, the less the company could
handle it. Right? Now, I've seen this at
banks or telcos, but Yahoo's a Silicon
Valley company less than 10 years old.
Why should it have this problem? Right?
And every big company has this problem.
If you're over 50 people, you have an
immune system problem. Why? Because all
organizations are built and architected
from Coase's law down for to do two
things. We're built for efficiency.
We're built for predictability. If you
look at every KPI in every big company
or medium-sized company in the world,
you'll see those two heuristics. Right?
There is no KPI for agility,
flexibility, adaptability, or speed.
Speed maybe. And yet those are the major
drivers of progress today.
Uh and we just as a quick segue, when we
launched the Exponential Organizations
book in 2014, in 2015, we scored the
Fortune 100 against this model. How
purpose-driven, agile, flexible,
adaptability org structures of the
Fortune 100. Okay? One of my community
members, Chander Nagpal, originally from
Delhi, worked did some work with UBS at
the time. So tracked for 7 years the top
10 of the Fortune 100. They used the
model the most and the bottom 10 they
used them the least. So, the most
flexible and agile versus the least
flexible, least agile in our against our
model, right? 7 years later, he adds up
the results. And the top 10 in the
Fortune 100, they used the model the
most, had delivered 40 times the
shareholder returns as the bottom 10.
>> Wow.
>> Not percent. Okay?
>> Mhm. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Times. Times.
>> We should have created an index fund. It
would have been the highest performing
fund ever. Why? Because as the external
world becomes more volatile, your
ability to adapt will drive market
value, right? Now, if you take that to
today's world,
you have to be flexible and adaptable,
but today you have to move towards being
AI native, okay? So, there's two
theoretical things you have to do.
Number one, you have to break that
immune system problem in your legacy
organization. If the mother keeps eating
the young, then you can't get to that
new state. Number two, the one way we
found of doing that is you never ever
ever ever try and do disruptive
innovation in the legacy organization.
You do it at the edge.
Okay?
So, I'll give you the example of
Nestlé, which created Nespresso in 1976.
For 10 years they ran it as a line of
business, okay?
>> Okay.
>> Inside the standard operating company,
big food processing company, foods, baby
food, diapers, etc. Didn't fit. It's a
different brand, different delivery,
different supply chain, different
customer system. Finally, the CEO gets
frustrated cuz they don't sit in any of
their normal management meetings with
the the lineup of the the other
division. He was just supposed to give
those guys a separate building, put them
away from the mostly just for the
annoyance of having to deal with this
different animal. And boom, over the
next few years every hotel room in the
world has an espresso machine and now
it's one of their highest margin lines
of business, right? You see the same
thing with Google breaking up into
Alphabet because our old thinking that
centralized coordinate activity and
coordinate execution and coordination
cost turns out to be flawed. You want to
decentralize today. So, what you do is
you take disruptive thinking at the edge
and you build at the edge, you run an
immune system blocker at the core. We
call ourselves Open EXO because we
open-sourced all of our methodologies.
Okay? So, we've actually published a
book called Exponential Transformation
that is a playbook for running that
10-week sprint. Literally tells you week
by week how to form teams, what homework
to give everybody, etc. etc. We've done
it with big companies now 100 times,
Black & Decker, HP, Visa, Siemens
Energy, etc. And we pull people from the
community to do the work. So, I have no
consultants on staff. Why? Because as a
community, we learn faster, right? And
we have very diversity of experiences.
So, just to go back to your original
question, there are two things you have
to do. One, run this immune system
process to block the
the legacy from attacking the new.
Secondly, create this
AI engine at the at the edge and start
moving workflows over one by one, okay?
In voice processing,
>> Yeah.
>> demand forecasting, content management,
little by little rebuild your
organization at the core of the
organization, and then you slow Once you
get recursive self-improvement at the
workflow level, you can start
deprecating the old.
Okay? And now, this is complex from a
management perspective. How do you get
the data, etc. And we're actually
running a pilot. We we put out a call
and said, "Look, we're going to work
with 10 CEOs."
And we're going to run this pilot with
them and take start helping them build
their workflows at the edge. We had like
almost 400 applicants for these 10
slots.
Where we picked the 10 and and one of
them is a small retailing company. And
we started We've got a retailing
company, we have a an escrow finance
company, we have a chemicals companies.
We've picked very different companies to
see how it works with different
industries, different companies. And at
the end, we'll see what the learnings
are and see how this works. Because I
don't see any other path for navigating
this. And here's the question I'm asking
every CEO in the world. Is there a high
margin line of business that two folks
of Open Law or Hermes can replicate in
60 or 90 days?
Okay? If the answer is yes, you've got
an existential threat. Sorry, that was a
long-winded answer.
>> that's perfectly explained. No,
perfectly explained. So, thank you for
that. Now, quickly, so let's say there
is a startup recently got seed fund, and
now they want to become like agent first
startup.
>> Yes.
>> Any advice any advice for those folks?
>> Yes, go to go register at Open AI, so
it's free. Download our cloud skill,
which is free.
>> Okay.
>> the skill will tell you, here's what to
tell you to do it. So, let me just talk
through this agentic layers that I've
come up with, okay?
We have six or seven layers in this
agent stack. So, number one is a purpose
layer that says, what is the purpose of
the company? More importantly, where
what is what won't the company do? What
are the boundary conditions from an
ethics point of view? Because we used to
have this concept, what is your massive
transformative purpose? It sat up as
like a poster on the wall. Uber is
everybody should have a private driver,
right? But AI agents aren't reading
posters on the wall. That MTP has to
become a protocol that an agent can read
and be very clear on what is the purpose
of the company. Okay? Next, you have a
sensing layer that says, what's
happening in the outside world? So, if
you're a retail company,
to use your example, and a competitor
suddenly announces same-day delivery.
Okay? The sensing layer is out there
scouring, goes, hey, competitor just
announced
same-day delivery. Passes that down to
the next level, which is an analysis
layer. Okay? What does this mean? How
big is that market? Do we think they're
going to succeed? How much of a threat
is this to our world? Which customer
channels get affected, etc. And and does
a bunch of analysis around how big is
that segment, how important do we think
it is, how big of a competitor threat it
is. It goes to a decision layer, right?
The decision layer now says, another
layer of it. Now, the C-suite at each
level is hitting keep going, go, go.
You've got humans above the loop doing
doing this kind of the thinking, the
judgment calls that is very critical,
which does not go away. At the decision
layer, you go, okay, do we ignore them
because we don't think the business is
really worth it? Do we compete? Do we
partner with a startup that's doing
same-day delivery? Do we acquire a
startup doing same-day delivery? What do
we do? Okay? Let's say you want to
partner with a startup that's doing
that. Now, you have an execution layer
that says, go find that startup,
negotiate a deal with them, etc. And
then finally, you have a learning loop
that says, how long did that whole loop
take? And next time we have a major
sensing and event, what can we do better
in that loop? Okay? So, that's the layer
loop. That's the core kind of layer of
engine. And then around the whole thing,
you have a very strong governance loop.
>> Okay.
>> Because every agent has to have
evaluation suites, it has to have human
review queue, uh log traceability and
and rollback recovery.
Okay? Because we could We've seen with
the agents, they go rogue, they lose
their work. They're like junior
employees, right? They stop for a coffee
or whatever, and then you've lost your
core thing. We So, that core engine that
gets created, and then you start
layering workflows on top of that. Okay?
And so, this is such a big shift for an
organization, going all the way back to
the design of the organization itself,
that you can never take an existing
organization and read fix it. Okay?
It goes all the way back to Buckminster
Fuller, who said, you can never fix an
existing system, you have to create new
systems at the edge, let that over time
become the new gravity well.
>> Okay.
>> You see this in Silicon Valley, where
Zuckerberg buys WhatsApp, buys
Instagram, leaves it on the edge,
right? And lets them grow, and then
you're building an ecosystem. In the
same way, you're rebuilding yourself in
this AI native way. I I don't see any
other methodology for doing it. If
you're a startup, you can just start
building from scratch.
>> Mhm.
>> If you're below 50 people and the CEO
has everybody on a first name basis,
brute force it. In a legacy organization
with over 50 people, you have to run
this immune system process,
build this thing at the edge, and start
building it. And frankly, there's no MBA
program that can teach you how to do
this.
>> Absolutely.
>> Let's note, there's no MBA program that
can even now that can teach you how to
build Uber.
>> Mhm.
>> MBA programs are still teaching 20th
century capabilities.
>> Absolutely, absolutely. People have to
unlearn
after learning after learning.
>> This is the
>> This is such a great point, right? You
have to unlearn and that's hard. And
this is where I think emerging markets
have such a massive opportunity. In the
US, Europe, Japan, we have to unlearn 50
years of Harvard MBA thinking and
relearn new models, right? Brazil,
India, the global south can just
leapfrog to these new models and I think
all the advantages will accrue the
faster you can So the holy grail is you
end up with a proprietary data and a and
a learning loop that every time you're
learning and that becomes your core
organizational asset is the ability to
constantly learn. Nobody will beat you
if you can get to that point.
>> Absolutely. Now, I think you are one of
your companies back in 2010 was acquired
by Google, right?
>> Yeah.
>> What What was that? Can you just let our
audience know?
>> my background from a I have a background
in software development and then a bit
of management consulting. I I I was in
Europe for all through the '90s. I came
to New York City in 1999 and built a
private equity I would ran a private
equity business and then started doing
tech startups. One of them was a publish
and subscribe uh matching engine. Okay?
And we solved a very important problem
at the time which was if a database runs
this problem in database design you have
what's called a many-to-many problem,
right? You may have many customers, many
products and you have to reconcile that.
It's usually done by the order who says
which customer bought which product. But
many-to-many is a nightmare from a
database perspective and database
systems resolve this problem at about
200 events per second. Okay? We designed
a matching algorithm that solved that
problem at 3 billion matches a second on
the desktop. Okay? It was like it was
like You know the Silicon Valley show
HBO's? We were like middleware
compression. We were
We were
this We lived the first few seasons of
that of that show base which is very
archetypal patterns. And and I got well
known for that. That's what led to me
being at Yahoo. And when I left Yahoo
one application for publish and
subscribe is uh was to figure out what
your friends are doing and and many
friends are doing the same thing. So the
thesis was if there's a new story about
Ashish, I want to know. If I have a
board member called Dan Berry, I want to
know, right? If there's news about him.
But there's Irish rugby players called
Dan Berry, there's cricketers called
Ashish. I'd want my guy not some random
news story. So what we did was we took
your LinkedIn profile, scoured the
internet for news stories about people
that you knew that were relevant to you.
And gave you back a Google news feed of
relevant articles and we used AI to
disambiguate that problem. And so
we started building it out and we got
the problem we ran into is LinkedIn
LinkedIn's API, which was our natural
thing, took too long to get published.
And by the time they did publish it, it
was so useless from a content functional
perspective that we basically And then
Google came along and said, "Look, we
need a contact management system for
Google Plus."
And so they acquired the company. So my
co-founder went to Google. I was doing
Singularity University by the time. So I
had to I kind of
did that, but we sold our company to
Google.
>> Okay. Okay. Now, one of the questions
like so right now people are doing
computer science in and and let's say
someone is in third year or the fourth
year and I have been hearing and I am
also believing that there could be some
impact of jobs, but people who want to
do work that there is plenty of work. So
can you give because you are coming from
the vast background, can you give some
of the ideas to these youngsters
what kind of work they can do after
finishing their computer science? Like
it could be something like download a
model, train that to a specific domain
or anything like that, right?
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. All of that.
Okay. So let me lift up to the macro
level. If you believe 10% of what I've
said that organizations will have to
change and my thesis is every single
organization in the world has to And
this is like 10 times bigger than the
internet, 10 times bigger than mobile,
10 times bigger than Y2K or anything.
Right? This is AI native organizations
are going to have the biggest impact in
the world over the next few years.
Employment is not dropping because we
need people to figure out how to
navigate every nonprofit, every
government department in the world. So,
that's why I'm not worried about the
broad macro job problem, okay?
>> Okay.
>> Now, if you're in third-year computer
science, I would do two things. First,
absolutely get trained up in AI,
>> Mhm.
>> download a model, start playing with it,
beg, borrow, and or steal the compute,
and just start get started.
Pick a problem that you're passionate
about, okay? It could be finding
colleague guitar players or sitar
players in my local area. Could be I I
have a I'm a tennis player, so finding
somebody to play tennis with is a is a
ongoing question for me, etc. And so,
find figure out what is tickles your
fancy is the most, and go build an AI
native system like that. If you don't
have something like that, go join an AI
startup, of which there were an
explosion today attacking a legacy
domain, and start working with them,
okay? So, either start or join an AI
startup, and your computer science
skills will be very, very, very
necessary. We There's a trope that, "Oh
my god, nobody needs to learn how to
code." No, you're
the computer science degree becomes very
powerful because you'll have better
judgment on what AIs are doing, how to
guide them in the coding than ever
before. All right, let me give you map
you my experience with writing books.
The first book was Exponential
Organizations. It's done very well. It's
almost a million copies sold, or maybe
it's just crossed that.
But it was 3 years of unadulterated
hell, okay? I hated the process. I'm not
a natural writer. I'm like a high-level
hand-waving guy. 80,000 words of detail
is anathema for me, okay? So, but and it
was a nightmare. Second book was 2 and
1/2 years of more hell because I kept
having to think how much of the first
book do I bring over. It's not a clean
build in a sense, right? This third book
was 3 months of absolute pure joy
because AI is doing all the cognitive
thinking. Satya Nadella just put out the
speech. How do I integrate it in the
book? Which quote should I pick? Where
should I insert it to make most logical
sense? AI does all that and I can just
go how much of a important is that
concept to what's relevant in the book?
And the AI handles all of the cognitive
workload and now it's absolutely pure
fun. That metaphor and that process now
applies to every software build ever in
history because think of anybody writing
software 10 years ago, 20 years ago, it
was hell, right? You spent wrote the
software, you wrote used the long
libraries, you had to rewrite it then
you went through bug fixing and that was
before you got to systems design then
you have to worry about user interface
and they would complain and you build it
the spec was wrong, the people who put
the the spec together didn't quite get
it right. So now you're frustrated
doubly. All that hell disappears, we can
just say oh new new user request, just
adapt all the code to make it work but
make sure you use these libraries etc.
So I think computer science becomes one
of the most demanded disciplines in the
future but it has to be you have to
shift your mindset to be AI native and
build things that are AI native from now
on.
>> Okay, perfect. Thank you so much Salim
for all your time. Very helpful, very
insightful as always.
Quick thing, how people can plug into
Open EXO? Is there is there a way like
people can plug into or yeah?
>> Go to openexo.com.
It's free to join.
And there we have all sorts of
resources, training. We have a pro
membership where people are are building
companies. We did weekly coaching with
them to help them through any issues.
>> Okay.
>> But you could but many of the resources
are available for free. The book is
free, the cloud school is free, you
know, that's we can't make it easier
than that.
>> Right. Thank you very much Salim,
always.
>> Great conversation.
>> All right, I'm loving it. Thank you so
much.